<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Georgina K. Cox</title>
    <link>http://georginacox.ca/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Georgina K. Cox</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Georgina K. Cox</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/project/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Cardiac Oxygen Supply and the Morphology of Shark Hearts</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/project/shark-hearts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/project/shark-hearts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this set of studies, I look at the the evolution of the cardiac oxygen supply using sharks as model system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://georginacox.ca/test/img/shark.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By exploring inter and intra-species variation in cardiovascular variables, I found that changes in vascular resistance could overcome the compressive forces of ventricular contraction in such a way that allows coronary blood flow to increase with heart rate despite the consequent increase in vascular compression by the surrounding myocardial tissue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By uncovering the mechanism which allows for the increased rate of oxygen delivery during elevated cardiac function I was able to detect similarities with mammalian cardiovascular function and identify a possible underlying mechanisms that may be phylogenetically conserved in vertebrates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, my morphological analysis of the coronary circulation across shark taxa using classical histological techniques combined with phylogenetic analysis and basic fluid dynamics led me to discover that temperature plays a role as a selective pressure on the design of vascular beds. This work provided novel insights into our understanding of the evolution of the coronary artery and cardiac oxygen delivery in vertebrates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cardiac function following oil exposure in pelagic fish</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/project/pelagic-fish/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/project/pelagic-fish/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During my postdoc as part of the RECOVER consortium, funded through GOMRI,  I have investigated whether phenotypic plasticity allows species to overcome anthropogenic sources of environmental pollution in the form of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAH’s), the toxic components of oil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://georginacox.ca/img/pres-fish.jpg&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this study I used a perfused heart technique to investigate the compensatory capacity of the cardiovascular system to overcome the reduced contractile function that results from acute PAH exposure in pelagic fish species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered an interactive effect between PAH exposure and adrenergic stimulation that suggested catecholamines could play a compensatory role that may help to mitigate adverse effects of PAH exposure on the heart &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My results indicated adrenergic nerve stimulation in combination with increased circulating catecholamines might be able to rescue cardiac function for brief periods in exposed individuals. However, a proportion of PAH exposed fish were unable to recover from maximal exertion despite elevated catecholamine levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research was the first to demonstrate that acute exposure to environmentally relevant concentrations of oil has profound effects on cardiovascular function at moderate to high levels of cardiac activity in athletic pelagic fish species. This research was presented locally for the general public, and nationally and internationally for the scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cardiovascular function of hagfish in anoxia (no oxygen) environments</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/project/hagfish/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/project/hagfish/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of vertebrate hearts can survive only minutes when cut off from oxygen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this study, and in conjunction with my work on cardiovascular responses to anoxia in hagfish, I discovered a number of diverse cardiovascular and biochemical phenotypes that permitted the survival of hagfish for &amp;gt;36h of complete oxygen deprivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered that hagfish were able to maintain routine metabolic rate for up to 6 hours of anoxia and that they subsequently utilized metabolic rate suppression to survive anoxic exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By using metabolic rate suppression hagfish met energy requirement using only their glycolytic capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I further discovered that in order to circulate the necessary glycolytic substrates and remove metabolic waste products from tissues the heart maintained function during anoxia. This was a particular surprise as cardiovascular function has traditionally been viewed as highly reliant on a stable oxygen supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My research in hagfish has lead to collaborations with other investigators that have since used hagfish to investigate physiological mechanisms of hypoxia and anoxia tolerance, and cardiovascular control mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
