<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Georgina K. Cox</title>
    <link>http://georginacox.ca/test/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Georgina K. Cox</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Georgina K. Cox</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/test/project/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of crude oil on cardiac function</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/test/project/crude-effects/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/test/project/crude-effects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exposure to polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAH) negatively impacts exercise performance in fish species but the physiological modifications that result in this phenotype are poorly understood. Prior studies have shown that embryonic and juvenile mahi–mahi (Coryphaeus hippurus) exposed to PAH exhibit morphological abnormalities, altered cardiac development and reduced swimming performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been suggested that cardiovascular function inhibited by PAH exposure accounts for the compromised exercise performance in fish species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this study we used in-situ techniques to measure hemodynamic responses of young adult mahi–mahi exposed to PAH for 24 h. The data indicate that stroke volume was reduced 44% in mahi–mahi exposed to 9.6 ± 2.7 μg l−1 geometric mean PAH (∑PAH) and resulted in a 39% reduction in cardiac output and a 52% reduction in stroke work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maximal change in pressure over change in time was 28% lower in mahi–mahi exposed to this level of ∑PAH. Mean intraventricular pressures and heart rate were not significantly changed. This study suggests exposure to environmentally relevant PAH concentrations impairs aspects of cardiovascular function in mahi–mahi.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hagfish</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/test/project/hagfish/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/test/project/hagfish/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pacific hagfish, Eptatretus stoutii, can recover from 36 h of anoxia at 10°C. Such anoxia tolerance demands the mobilization of anaerobic fuels and the removal of metabolic wastes – processes that require a functional heart. The purpose of this study was to measure the metabolic response of the excised, cannulated hagfish heart to anoxia using direct calorimetry. These experiments were coupled with measurements of cardiac pH and metabolite concentrations, at multiple time points, to monitor acid–base balance and anaerobic ATP production. We also exposed hagfish to anoxia to compare the in vitro responses of the excised hearts with the in vivo responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The calorimetry results revealed a significant reduction in the rate of metabolic heat production over the first hour of anoxia exposure, and a recovery over the subsequent 6 h. This response is likely attributable to a rapid anoxia-induced depression of aerobic ATP-production pathways followed by an upregulation of anaerobic ATP-production pathways such that the ATP production rate was restored to that measured in normoxia. Glycogen-depletion measurements suggest that metabolic processes were initially supported by glycolysis but that an alternative fuel source was used to support the sustained rates of ATP production. The maintenance of intracellular pH during anoxia indicates a remarkable ability of the myocytes to buffer/regulate protons and thus protect cardiac function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Altogether, these results illustrate that the low metabolic demand of the hagfish heart allows for near-routine levels of cardiac metabolism to be supported anaerobically. This is probably a significant contributor to the hagfish’s exceptional anoxia tolerance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morphology of Shark Hearts</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/test/project/shark-hearts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/test/project/shark-hearts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The coronary circulation first appeared in the chordate lineage in cartilaginous fishes where, as in birds and mammals but unlike most teleost fishes, it supplies arterial blood to the entire myocardium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://georginacox.ca/test/test/img/shark.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the pivotal position of elasmobranch fishes in the evolution of the coronary circulation, the determinants of coronary blood flow have never been investigated in this group. Elasmobranch fishes are of special interest because of the morphological arrangement of their cardiomyocytes. Unlike teleosts, the majority of the ventricular myocardium in elasmobranch fishes is distant to the venous blood returning to the heart (i.e., the luminal blood).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the majority of the myocardium is in close association with the coronary circulation. To determine the relative contribution of the coronary and luminal blood supplies to cardiovascular function in sandbar sharks, Carcharhinus plumbeus, we measured coronary blood flow while manipulating cardiovascular status using acetylcholine and adrenaline.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
