<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Georgina K. Cox</title>
    <link>http://georginacox.ca/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Georgina K. Cox</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Georgina K. Cox</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/publication/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Oil Exposure Impairs In Situ Cardiac Function in Response to β-Adrenergic Stimulation in Cobia (Rachycentron canadum)</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/publication/oil-exposure-cobia-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/publication/oil-exposure-cobia-2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://georginacox.ca/img/fish-oil.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cardio-respiratory function during exercise in the cobia, Rachycentron canadum: The impact of crude oil exposure.</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/publication/crude-oil-exposure-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/publication/crude-oil-exposure-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Determinants of coronary blood flow in sandbar sharks, Carcharhinus plumbeus</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/publication/sand-bar-shark-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/publication/sand-bar-shark-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of crude oil on in situ cardiac function in young adult mahi-mahi (Coryphaena hippurus)</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/publication/crude-mahi-mahi-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/publication/crude-mahi-mahi-2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing a novel mechanism to control heart rate in the ancestral Pacific hagfish</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/publication/ancestral-hagfish-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/publication/ancestral-hagfish-2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://georginacox.ca/img/hagfish1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Composite of 70 images showing sAC in the sinus venosus from a larger hagfish; the boxed areas are shown at higher magnification in i–v. In the higher-magnification images, the left panels are differential interference contrast, and the scale bars represent 50 µm. sAC immunostaining is in red; nuclei are stained in blue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morphological arrangement of the coronary vasculature in a shark (Squalus sucklei) and a teleost (Oncorhynchus mykiss)</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/publication/coronary-vasculature-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/publication/coronary-vasculature-2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing the metabolic capacity of the anoxic hagfish heart.</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/publication/anoxic-hagfish-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/publication/anoxic-hagfish-2015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hagfish are benthic fishes that spend considerable periods of time buried in the sediment and the putrefying carcasses of aquatic animals where they feed (Lesser et al., 1997; Martini, 1998). These environments are routinely hypoxic and even anoxic, so it is unsurprising that hagfish display an exceptional tolerance to hypoxia and anoxia. Hansen and Sidell (1983) demonstrated that anoxia and cyanide poisoning did not have an effect on the in situ function of the heart from the Atlantic hagfish Myxine glutinosa. Similarly, the Pacific hagfish Eptatretus stoutii has been shown to tolerate 36 h of anoxia at 10°C with a regular heartbeat and full recovery (Cox et al., 2010, 2011). Long-term anoxic survival like this demands the maintenance of certain organ functions within the animal, and one such critical organ is the heart. The maintenance of cardiac function under anoxic conditions allows for the mobilization of metabolic fuel stores (e.g. glycogen) from storage tissues (e.g. liver) and the removal of waste from metabolically active tissues (Stecyk et al., 2008). These two functions are critical to the anoxic survival of the animal and indeed, Cox et al. (2010) found that these are well maintained in anoxic hagfish: cardiac power output, a proxy for energy usage, decreased by only 25% in hagfish exposed to 36 h of anoxia. The maintenance of anoxic cardiac function in hagfish is thought to be associated with a relatively low cardiac metabolic requirement (Forster, 1991), such that the hagfish heart&amp;rsquo;s routine power output – the lowest ever measured in a fish – is within the heart&amp;rsquo;s maximum glycolytic potential (Farrell and Stecyk, 2007). The importance of glycolytic pathways to cardiac function in hagfish was demonstrated by Hansen and Sidell (1983). Using an in situ preparation on Atlantic hagfish, they found that despite inhibition of cardiac mitochondrial function with cyanide or sodium azide, cardiac output was maintained for at least 3 h. However, inhibiting glycolytic function with iodoacetate resulted in a significant decrease in cardiac output. The authors also found that the activity ratio of the enzymes pyruvate kinase (PK) to cytochrome c oxidase (CO) were 5.6-fold higher in the hagfish ventricle compared with that of cod. This was interpreted as the hagfish ventricle having a ‘more anaerobically geared’ metabolism (Hansen and Sidell, 1983). Together, these results suggest that anaerobic glycolysis plays an important role in maintaining cardiac function, and thus survival, in the anoxic hagfish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the glycolytic capacity of the hagfish heart is thought to be capable of supporting routine cardiac function, and because this cardiac function is well maintained in anoxic environments, we hypothesized that the metabolic rate of the hagfish heart would be similarly maintained in anoxic environments. We tested this hypothesis by performing direct calorimetry on the excised, cannulated hearts of Pacific hagfish, E. stoutii, which are capable of beating for at least 24 h post-excision under anoxic conditions (Wilson, 2014). Direct calorimetry – the measurement of heat produced by, in this case, an excised heart – was used because it is the only technique that enables the continuous measurement of metabolic rate under anoxic conditions. In addition to the calorimetry measurements, we ran additional parallel anoxic exposures on excised, cannulated hearts and sampled them at three time points throughout the exposures to measure a variety of cardiac metabolites: lactate and glycogen levels were measured to estimate reliance on anaerobic ATP-production pathways, and intracellular pH (pHi) was measured to determine how the heart&amp;rsquo;s ability to maintain acid–base balance was influenced by anoxic exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the excised heart experiments, we exposed two groups of hagfish to 36 h of normoxia and anoxia. Hagfish heart tissue was analysed for the same metabolites described above and blood was analysed for a number of haematological parameters. This allowed us to compare the response of the in vitro heart with that of the in vivo heart, which was important because the in vitro heart would experience an almost immediate lack of O2 upon induction of environmental anoxia, whereas in vivo, the heart becomes progressively hypoxic until true anoxia is reached when the fish&amp;rsquo;s large O2 stores are depleted; this could take a considerable period of time given the hagfish&amp;rsquo;s low haemoglobin P50 value [∼7–12 mmHg PO2 (Wells et al., 1986; Forster et al., 1992)], large blood volume and low metabolic rate (Cox et al., 2010, 2011). This fact made the in vivo exposures especially important to testing our hypothesis that metabolic activity is maintained in the hagfish heart during prolonged periods of anoxia.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The beat goes on: Cardiac pacemaking in extreme conditions.</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/publication/extreme-pacemaking-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/publication/extreme-pacemaking-2015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hagfish are benthic fishes that spend considerable periods of time buried in the sediment and the putrefying carcasses of aquatic animals where they feed (Lesser et al., 1997; Martini, 1998). These environments are routinely hypoxic and even anoxic, so it is unsurprising that hagfish display an exceptional tolerance to hypoxia and anoxia. Hansen and Sidell (1983) demonstrated that anoxia and cyanide poisoning did not have an effect on the in situ function of the heart from the Atlantic hagfish Myxine glutinosa. Similarly, the Pacific hagfish Eptatretus stoutii has been shown to tolerate 36 h of anoxia at 10°C with a regular heartbeat and full recovery (Cox et al., 2010, 2011). Long-term anoxic survival like this demands the maintenance of certain organ functions within the animal, and one such critical organ is the heart. The maintenance of cardiac function under anoxic conditions allows for the mobilization of metabolic fuel stores (e.g. glycogen) from storage tissues (e.g. liver) and the removal of waste from metabolically active tissues (Stecyk et al., 2008). These two functions are critical to the anoxic survival of the animal and indeed, Cox et al. (2010) found that these are well maintained in anoxic hagfish: cardiac power output, a proxy for energy usage, decreased by only 25% in hagfish exposed to 36 h of anoxia. The maintenance of anoxic cardiac function in hagfish is thought to be associated with a relatively low cardiac metabolic requirement (Forster, 1991), such that the hagfish heart&amp;rsquo;s routine power output – the lowest ever measured in a fish – is within the heart&amp;rsquo;s maximum glycolytic potential (Farrell and Stecyk, 2007). The importance of glycolytic pathways to cardiac function in hagfish was demonstrated by Hansen and Sidell (1983). Using an in situ preparation on Atlantic hagfish, they found that despite inhibition of cardiac mitochondrial function with cyanide or sodium azide, cardiac output was maintained for at least 3 h. However, inhibiting glycolytic function with iodoacetate resulted in a significant decrease in cardiac output. The authors also found that the activity ratio of the enzymes pyruvate kinase (PK) to cytochrome c oxidase (CO) were 5.6-fold higher in the hagfish ventricle compared with that of cod. This was interpreted as the hagfish ventricle having a ‘more anaerobically geared’ metabolism (Hansen and Sidell, 1983). Together, these results suggest that anaerobic glycolysis plays an important role in maintaining cardiac function, and thus survival, in the anoxic hagfish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the glycolytic capacity of the hagfish heart is thought to be capable of supporting routine cardiac function, and because this cardiac function is well maintained in anoxic environments, we hypothesized that the metabolic rate of the hagfish heart would be similarly maintained in anoxic environments. We tested this hypothesis by performing direct calorimetry on the excised, cannulated hearts of Pacific hagfish, E. stoutii, which are capable of beating for at least 24 h post-excision under anoxic conditions (Wilson, 2014). Direct calorimetry – the measurement of heat produced by, in this case, an excised heart – was used because it is the only technique that enables the continuous measurement of metabolic rate under anoxic conditions. In addition to the calorimetry measurements, we ran additional parallel anoxic exposures on excised, cannulated hearts and sampled them at three time points throughout the exposures to measure a variety of cardiac metabolites: lactate and glycogen levels were measured to estimate reliance on anaerobic ATP-production pathways, and intracellular pH (pHi) was measured to determine how the heart&amp;rsquo;s ability to maintain acid–base balance was influenced by anoxic exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the excised heart experiments, we exposed two groups of hagfish to 36 h of normoxia and anoxia. Hagfish heart tissue was analysed for the same metabolites described above and blood was analysed for a number of haematological parameters. This allowed us to compare the response of the in vitro heart with that of the in vivo heart, which was important because the in vitro heart would experience an almost immediate lack of O2 upon induction of environmental anoxia, whereas in vivo, the heart becomes progressively hypoxic until true anoxia is reached when the fish&amp;rsquo;s large O2 stores are depleted; this could take a considerable period of time given the hagfish&amp;rsquo;s low haemoglobin P50 value [∼7–12 mmHg PO2 (Wells et al., 1986; Forster et al., 1992)], large blood volume and low metabolic rate (Cox et al., 2010, 2011). This fact made the in vivo exposures especially important to testing our hypothesis that metabolic activity is maintained in the hagfish heart during prolonged periods of anoxia.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Perspective on the Evolution of the Coronary Circulation in Fishes and the Transition to Terrestrial Life</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/publication/fish-circulation-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/publication/fish-circulation-2012/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anoxic survival of the Pacific hagfish (Eptatretus stoutii)</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/publication/anoxic-hagfish-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/publication/anoxic-hagfish-2011/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cardiac responses to anoxia in the Pacific hagfish, Eptatretus stoutii.</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/publication/anoxic-hagfish-2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/publication/anoxic-hagfish-2010/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Only a few of the more than 25,000 species of fishes are known to be tolerant of severe hypoxia, and even anoxia. Even so, there are representatives among cyclostomes, elasmobranchs and teleosts. Among teleosts, the carp family has several hypoxia-tolerant species, e.g. the common carp, Cyprinus carpio (Stecyk and Farrell, 2002; Stecyk et al., 2004) and the tilapia, Oreochromis hybrid sp. (Speers-Roesch et al., 2010), but the crucian carp, Carassius carassius, stands out as being tolerant of anoxia for days to weeks at temperatures of 5–8°C (Hyvärinen et al., 1985; Nilsson, 1990; Nilsson, 2001; Shoubridge and Hochachka, 1980; Stecyk et al., 2004; Vornanen and Tuomennoro, 1999). The most hypoxia-tolerant elasmobranch appears to be the epaulette shark, Hemiscyllium ocellatum, which can withstand hours of severe hypoxia at 25°C (Nilsson and Renshaw, 2004; Stenslokken et al., 2004; Wise et al., 1998). Among cyclostomes, hagfishes routinely inhabit oxygen-depleted environments, such as hypoxic sediments. In addition, their feeding strategy of burrowing into the coelomic cavities of dead or moribund animals exposes them to short periods of severe hypoxia or anoxia (Axelsson et al., 1990; Forster et al., 1992; Perry et al., 1993; Perry et al., 2009). However, whether or not hagfishes are anoxia tolerant is unclear, although there are certainly suggestions that the heart can function under anoxic conditions (Forster, 1991; Hansen and Sidell, 1983).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the possibility that hagfishes might be anoxia tolerant, the objective of the present study was to characterize the cardiac responses in the Pacific hagfish, Eptatretus stoutii (Lockington 1878), to prolonged anoxia because most vertebrate hearts do not tolerate even severe hypoxia. It has been suggested that the ability to maintain cardiac function without sufficient oxygen requires a low routine cardiac power output and ATP demand, a high cardiac glycolytic potential and a means of dealing with anaerobic wastes (Farrell, 1991b; Farrell and Stecyk, 2007). In this regard, hagfishes are recognized as having the lowest cardiac power output among all fishes (Farrell, 2007a), an in vitro or in situ cardiac glycolytic potential that can serve these needs (Forster, 1991; Hansen and Sidell, 1983) and a blood volume larger than any vertebrate (Forster et al., 2001).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the cardiovascular features of hagfish suggest that they could maintain cardiac performance during prolonged periods of anoxia, the requisite measurements of cardiac power output, the product of ventral aortic blood flow and pressure, are lacking. Instead, such measurements have been limited to severely hypoxic hagfishes for a period of 30 min or less. Under these conditions, cardiac output was maintained or slightly increased in the Atlantic hagfish, Myxine glutinosa, and the New Zealand hagfish, Eptatretus cirrhatus (Axelsson et al., 1990; Forster et al., 1992). Furthermore, Hansen and Sidell (Hansen and Sidell, 1983) had earlier shown that the gross mechanical activity (frequency and force of heart beat) of an in situ heart was maintained in anaesthetized M. glutinosa for 3 h after cardiac poisoning with either cyanide or azide to stop mitochondrial respiration, as well as during severe hypoxia (gills perfused with nitrogen-equilibrated water). However, given that the majority of hypoxia-tolerant vertebrates reduce cardiac power output by 50–95% during severe hypoxia, the only exception being crucian carp (Stecyk et al., 2004), there is the possibility that hagfish, extant representatives of fish with the most primitive chambered heart, also depress cardiac power output during prolonged anoxia. Thus, the purpose of this study was to test the hypothesis that the Pacific hagfish, like the crucian carp, maintain cardiac performance during prolonged anoxia.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Circulatory limits to oxygen supply during an acute temperature increase in the Chinook salmon (Oncorhynchus tshawytscha)</title>
      <link>http://georginacox.ca/publication/circ-limits-salmon/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://georginacox.ca/publication/circ-limits-salmon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;with current trends in climate change, it is becoming increasingly important to understand both the behavioral and physiological responses of animals to perturbations in temperature (41). The highly efficient counter-current arrangement between blood and respiratory water at fish gills means that any acute change in ambient water temperature rapidly changes body temperature and modifies tissue oxygen requirements (10–13, 43, 58). A change in the rate of oxygen consumption (ṀO2) then requires a parallel change in oxygen delivery from the gills to tissues by the circulatory system, which is determined by the product of cardiac output (Q) and the difference between arterial (CaO2) and venous (CvO2) oxygen content (CaO2-CvO2) according to the Fick equation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://georginacox.ca/test/img/fig/fick.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q is the product of heart rate (fH) and cardiac stroke volume (VS), while CaO2-CvO2 is dependent on oxygen partial pressure and capacitance of the blood for oxygen. Blood oxygen capacitance itself is reliant on mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration (MCHC), oxygen binding characteristics, and the degree of saturation of the hemoglobin molecule (62). Thus, changes in circulatory oxygen delivery resulting from variations in body temperature can be modulated by changes in one or any combination of these factors (18). In the present study, we were particularly interested in circulatory oxygen delivery because it has been suggested that circulatory performance of fishes may be the first process to cause oxygen deficiency during heat stress (40, 50). However, while many studies have investigated components of the cardiorespiratory response to heat stress in fish, the composite response has rarely been measured in a single study. Furthermore, a range of responses are reported, perhaps reflecting species variability and/or subtle but important differences in the experimental protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
